Yesterday was the last day of the rest
of our lives. Yesterday was the day Sam
Olman asked his ego this three-word
question. What have we done? Because
yesterday was the day the human
intelligence monopoly officially ended
with the long-awaited release of
OpenAI's GPT5, the first AI model to
outperform biological humans on the
Simple Bench benchmark. Meanwhile, it's
quickly overtaking virtually every
leaderboard on LM Marina, which means
every programmer that still has a job
will be getting a layoff notice shortly.
Or at least that's what the hype
engineers at OpenAI want you to think.
Not everybody is falling for it, though.
That simple bench score was just a
rumor. And in fact, GPT5 is actually in
fifth place. GPT5 failed to beat Grock
on the ARC AGI benchmark, an important
benchmark that was conveniently left out
of yesterday's announcement. It also
underwhelmed the betting markets, and
OpenAI is no longer the favorite to have
the best model of 2025. Worst of all
though, people found numerous problems
with OpenAI's own charts, which really
shouldn't happen when you have PhD level
intelligence in your pocket. In today's
video, we'll find out if GPT5 is just
another overhyped incremental upgrade or
a true game changer, edging us closer to
artificial super intelligence. It is
August 8th, 2025, and you're watching
the code report. In the past, GPT got
better as it got bigger. It was trained
on more data that would activate more
parameters when generating text. But
those days are essentially over. The
thing that makes GPT5 special is not
that it's a bigger, smarter model, but
rather it unifies multiple models like
fast reasoning, routing, etc. to pick
the right tool per task without the end
user needing to think about it. In many
ways, GPT5 feels more like a
consolidation and cost reduction effort
after they spent the last year panic
shipping a bunch of stupidly named
models to justify the $200 pro plan.
Speaking of cost though, GPT5 is priced
at only $10 per million output tokens.
And that's a great deal compared to
Claude Opus 4.1, which will burn a hole
in your wallet at $75 per million output
tokens. Sam Alman says GBT5 is like
having multiple PhD level experts in
your pocket. But one of the funniest
parts of their announcement is that
their benchmark graphics were presented
with a y-axis that doesn't make any
sense. And there can only be two
possible explanations for this error.
One, they vibe charted with GPT5 and it
doesn't actually have PhD level
intelligence. Or two, they were trying
to be intentionally misleading. What's
even better is that GPT5 is supposed to
have lower deception rates, but then
someone or something tried to deceive us
with the Y-axis on the deception
benchmark. And that's kind of
embarrassing for a $500 billion
intelligence company. But if you're a
programmer, the biggest question is
whether or not GPT5 can code a spelt 5
to app with runes. Many models have come
close, but none have succeeded. I put
GPT5 to the test and was stunned to see
that it generated beautiful looking
spill code and did so very quickly, far
faster than any other reasoning model.
At first, I thought I was working with a
PhD level spelt developer, but I would
soon be disappointed after running the
code and getting a 500 error as the UI.
What's troubling is that GPT5 used the
right syntax, but tried to use a rune in
the template, which is not allowed. GPT5
is supposed to have fewer
hallucinations, but it hallucinated its
own rules for using runes. However, it
did redeem itself when I asked if it
knew what was wrong with its code, at
which point it figured it out and fixed
it. And the end result is a functional
app that has a very nicel looking UI. I
also had it build a flight simulator
game with 3JS, which turned out pretty
bad. But the tall guy from Cursor said
it's the smartest model they've ever
used. Unfortunately though, I don't
think GPT5 is going to take my job or
euthanize me anytime soon. Because it's
clear at this point that the real power
comes when you combine these new AI
tools with existing technologies that
you already know and love. Which is why
you need to check out DreamFlow. with
the sponsor of today's video. It's a
full stack AI development environment
created by the team at Flutterflow that
lets you build, run, and deploy
cross-platform apps all from your
browser. You can spin up a new project
with a prompt and it'll run directly in
DreamFlow where you'll get full file
system access along with the ability to
preview and edit all of your pages and
components either by using their visual
editor or manually changing the code
yourself. It integrates seamlessly with
Firebase and Superbase and also lets you
deploy to the web or the app stores with
a single click. If someone would have
shown me this when I was first getting
into Flutter back in 2018, my brain
would have exploded. But you can try out
Dreamflow for free with the link below.
This has been the Code Report. Thanks
for watching and I will see you in the
next one.